Sincearosこちら is free to play all of the games,
Sincearosこちら is free to play all of the games,
the distribution of the fantastic Dug Its
the distribution of the fantastic Dug Its
modified
modified
stone
stone
lecture starts
演講會開始
We ask Vice President Wang Huijun to host for us
我們請王惠君副院長為我們主持
clap your hands
拍掌
Thank you for listening to our knowledge quiz
謝謝各位來聽我們的這個知識想驗
We think every knowledge test is very good
我們覺得每一次知識想驗都非常的好
Today I want to say good night first
今天我要先說一聲晚安
so today we are happy
那麼今天我們很高興
We invite Professor Zhang Wen
我們請到張文教授
Our fellows are part of the Academia Sinica
我們的研究員是中央研究院分職
Researcher at the Institute of Biology
生物研究所的研究員
Come tell us a story about this virus
來跟我們講這個病毒相關的故事
he got good grades
他的題目取得很好
virus is with you
病毒就在你身邊
Maybe it's with us now
也許現在就在我們的身邊
But his English is also very good
不過他的英文也很好
Surfing with the viruses
Surfing with the viruses
I think everyone is quite aware of the virus
我想病毒各位都相當的清楚
what's going on
是怎麼一回事
But Teacher Zhang Wen is an expert among experts in this field
不過張文老師他是這一方面專家中的專家
So we are very happy to have this opportunity
所以我們很高興能夠有這個機會
Please come to him and talk us deep forward out of the way
請到他來跟我們深入前出的方式
Come tell us some stories about this virus
來跟我們介紹這個病毒的一些相關的故事
either knowledge or
也好 或者知識也好
Teacher Zhang Wen is from the Department of Agrochemicals, National Taiwan University
張文老師是台大農化系
When I graduated in 1982
畢業的1982年的時候
Go to the U.S. after graduation
畢業完了以後到美國
是University of Washington
是University of Washington
I Washington University
I Washington University
University of Washington
University of Washington
University of Washington in Washington
華盛頓大學在華盛頓
west america university
西亞特那大學
Get a Ph.D. in hygiene and immunology
得到衛生物還有免疫學的博士
Then to Mashenri Public School
之後到馬神里公學院
go to cancer center
去做癌症中心
doing postdoctoral research
做博士後的研究
I saw where he went in 1989
我看到他是1989年去哪個地方
I had already left by then
那時候我已經離開了
So I didn't overlap with you
所以沒有跟你overlap
After Zhang Wen returned to Taiwan
張文回台以後
in our avatar
就在我們分身所
I always talk about biochemistry
我老是要講生化所
Excuse me
不好意思
That doppelgänger is almost gone
那個分身所都差不多了
do research
做研究
There have been very outstanding results along the way.
一路過來有非常傑出的這種成果
Then I won the outstanding awards from everyone in this country, etc.
那麼也得過這個國各位的傑出獎等等
So important is our kind
那麼重要的也是我們這種
Internationally
在國際上
if you want a
如果你要有一個
This well-known reader is often invited to such international journals
這個知名讀常常就會被邀請到國際的這種期刊
Journal Virology
Journal Virology
And the editorial board members of the two journals of Virology
還有這個Virology兩個雜誌的編輯委員
it's not easy
這是相當不容易的事情
So do we warmly welcome our Professor Zhang Wen to talk to us today?
所以我們今天是不是熱烈歡迎我們這個張文教授來跟我們講
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, Dean Wang Fu
謝謝王夫院長
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
I am very glad to have this opportunity to talk to you about the virus today
我今天很高興有這個機會來跟大家談一下病毒
In fact, today's topic is called Virus is by your side
那其實今天的題目叫病毒就在你身邊
this is the wind
這是風
That topic today is the virus is by your side
那題目今天是病毒就在你身邊
Well, today’s topic is actually not about all viruses.
那今天這個題目其實我不是談所有的病毒
Well, I've been doing virus research for about twenty years.
那我做病毒研究做了大概二十年
then my favorite virus
然後我最喜歡的病毒
So today I'm going to force you to share with me
那今天我要強迫大家跟我分享
that's a pox virus
那就是一個痘病毒
Well, this pox virus is actually no stranger in our history.
那這個痘病毒其實在我們的歷史裡面是不陌生的
So let's just talk about this virus with a few stories
那所以我們只是藉著幾個小故事談一談這個病毒
that has something to do with us
那跟我們人的關係
so let's talk about
所以我們先講一下說
Why do I have to say in my title
為什麼我的題目裡面要講說
virus is with you
病毒就在你身邊
Well I think basically the concept
好我想基本上的那個觀念
It is because the virus is very small
就在於是說因為病毒很小
Excuse me
不好意思
because the virus is small
因為病毒很小
so when it's next to us
所以它在我們旁邊的時候
Actually we don't know
其實我們都不知道
The second is to say
那第二個就是說
Because of the virus, it actually follows the footsteps
因為病毒它其實跟著記足走
so it's always next to us
所以它 always 在我們的旁邊
it's not like bacteria
它不像細菌
Bacteria can replicate without us
細菌離開我們還可以複製
But the virus is real time
可是病毒是實時刻刻
must remember
必須要在記住
so it's actually wrapping around
所以它實際上是一直在環繞
by our side
在我們的身邊
the most important one is
那最重要的一個是
it's everywhere
它無所不在
So along with remembering it's actually everywhere
所以隨著記住它其實到處都是
So in fact, to avoid such a
所以其實要去避免這樣子的一個
a virus
一個病毒
next to us
在我們的旁邊
almost very difficult
幾乎上是非常難的
let me make an example
那我打一個比方
How about a virus
病毒怎麼個小法
we all know
我們大家都知道
The definition of a virus is
病毒的定義是
Able to pass through some filtering instruments
能夠通過一些濾過性的一些儀器
If I make an analogy here
那如果我這邊打一個比方
Here is the cowpea virus that we often experiment with
這裡是我們常常做實驗的牛豆病毒
is a fighting virus
是一個鬥病毒
Its size is only about 350nm
它的大小大概只有350nm
nano is 10 to the negative 9th power
nano是10的負9次方
So in fact we can't see it with an optical microscope
所以事實上我們用光學顯微機看不見
Then you have to use the electron microscope
然後一定要用到電子顯微鏡
magnification optical microscope
放大的倍數光學顯微鏡
About usually 100x to 400x
大概通常是100倍到400倍
is invisible
是看不見的
Usually we have to enter tens of thousands of times
通常我們要進到上萬倍
or 50,000 times
或者是5萬倍
so you can start to see the shape
那這樣你才可以開始看得到它的形狀
The structure is still very unclear.
那這個結構其實還是非常的不清楚
Often times you have to re-enter
通常很多時候你還要再進到
The so-called diffraction of X-rays
所謂的X光的繞射
or more sophisticated instruments
或者是更其他的精細的儀器
You can see the structure on its surface
你才能看得到它表面的結構
so it's actually very, very small
所以它其實非常非常的小
The second one is that we have measured
那第二個就是我們曾經測量過
Collaborate with Mr. Zhang Hongzheng
跟張宏正老師合作
measured the mass of the virus
測量過這個病毒它的質量
The quality of the virus
那這個病毒的質量
a particle
一個particle
If it is a particle, it is probably
它一個顆粒的話大概
it has very little mass
它的質量非常少
5 out of 10 minus 15 grams
5成10的負15次克
If the algorithm is called 5 final grains
如果用算法叫做5個fintal grain
In simple terms
那簡單的量來講的話
That number might sound like...
這個數字大概聽起來很...
let's talk about it
那我們就這樣講好了
if you just imagine a
如果你就想像一個
After playing a spray T
打了一個噴T之後
The sprayed mist
噴出去的這個霧狀的
In terms of volume
大概體積來講的話
probably a microliter
大概是一個microliter
Let's talk about its volume
那我們就講說它的體積
If its density is 1 then
如果它的密度就是1的話
you squirt out
你打噴T出去
the number of viruses on it
那上面的病毒的數量
possibly hundreds of millions
可能會到幾億顆
So in this case
所以在這個情況之下的話
In fact, in our daily life, we often
其實我們常常在日常生活
Walking without knowing it 24 hours a day
24小時不知不覺都在散步
something like this
這樣子的東西
Of course
那當然啊
That scientist likes to tune a book
那個科學家都喜歡調個書
talking about why we do these studies
在說為什麼我們要做這些研究
It's good to take the opportunity to promote
趁機推銷一下也好
Of course everyone can think of that one
那一個當然大家都可以想得到
is in our life
就是我們的生活中
Since viruses are everywhere
既然病毒無所不在
to our life
對我們的生活
to our health
對我們的健康
to our economy
對我們的經濟
will definitely have some impact
一定會造成一些影響
that many examples
那很多的例子
everyone can imagine
大家都可以想得到
Every day when I open the newspaper
每天翻開報紙的時候
flu virus
流感病毒
or hepatitis virus
或者是肝炎病毒
These are all imaginable
這些都是可以想見到的
that for those of us who do the research
那對我們做研究的人而言
when walking into the experiment
走進實驗的時候
Viruses have another layer on us
病毒對我們還有另一層
attraction
吸引力
That is to say, because of his simplicity
也就是說是因為他的簡單
his small his simple
他的小他的簡單
When we study to understand the origin of life
我們在研究想要了解生命的起源的時候
When wanting to understand something about the mechanisms that work in our body
想要了解一些在我們身體裡面運作的機制的時候
In fact, viruses are a very good biological system to start with.
其實病毒是一個非常好的入手的一個生物系統
Let me use an example
那我打比方來講好了
we all know by now
我們大家現在都知道是說
composition of life words
生命的組成的話
a lot of deoxyribonucleic acid
很多是去氧核糖核酸
that was in 1960
那在1960年的時候
This is a Central Dog
這個是一個 Central Dog
it's immutable
就是這是不可改變的
But in fact the first evidence
可是事實上第一個證據
An extension of this concept is the reverse entry virus
擴展的這個觀念的就是反轉入病毒
His Geno
他的Geno
That means his genome is not actually a DN
就是說他的基因組其實不是DN是
We're talking about ribonucleic acid
我們講的去是核糖核酸
So this is overturned
所以這個是推翻了
The idea that DNA is the only genome
DNA是唯一一個基因組的一個觀念
That's inside a virus
那就是一個病毒裡面的
his genome
他的基因組
Here is an example
這是一個例子
The second one said that everyone is very concerned about it now.
那第二個說大家現在都很關心說
The treatment of cancer or the origin of cancer
癌症的治療或者癌症的起源
In fact, the earliest to know
那事實上最早能夠知道說
when cancer occurs
癌症的發生的時候
also caused by a virus
也是在一個病毒引起的一個
body of a muscle
一個肌的身上
that produced a gene
那產生了一個基因
The gene brought in by this virus is called SARC
那這個病毒帶進去的基因叫做SARC
what about this
那這個呢
it will make the muscle body
它會讓肌的身上
generate some meat flow
產生一些肉流
So it's from the genes like this
所以就是從這樣子的基因
Everyone is starting to realize
大家開始發覺到說
original cell regulation of cell division
原來細胞的調控細胞的分裂
may be caused by
有可能是造成
The real cause of so-called cancer
所謂癌症的其實的原因
all these are
這些都是
some of the creatures we grew up with
一些我們從小的生物
something like a virus
像病毒這樣子的東西
Extend some of its principles
延伸出來它的一些原則
draw some of its conclusions
延伸出來一些它的結論
Then you can start applying it to larger
然後開始可以把它應用到比較大的
some
一些的
Inside complex biological systems
複雜的生物的系統裡面
so this is for us
所以這是這是對我們而言
Doing research is actually very, very
做研究的是其實是非常非常具有
a property of attraction
吸引力的一個性質
Of course, there is another one mentioned in the middle
那當然中間還有一個提到我們講
That is to say, the virus must survive
就是說病毒要生存
this is it
這個是它
we talk about the selfish gene
我們講自私的基因
it's the only law
就是這是唯一的法則
it has to survive
它要生存
so it has a very important
所以它有一個非常重要
very important feature
非常重要的特性
is that it often mutates
就是它常常突變
that everyone thinks
那個大家都認為說
Women are fickle
女人善變
people are fickle
人也善變
Children are also fickle
小孩子也善變
mom said
媽媽說
My child is the most fickle
我的小孩最善變
But the fact is that viruses are very fickle.
可是呢事實上病毒是非常善變
That's one of the strengths of our research
那這也是我們研究它的一個力氣
Because of its fickleness and its adaptation and its evolution
因為它的善變跟它的適應跟它的演化
There is an inseparable relationship between
中間有不可密切的關係
study its changes
研究它的改變
Help us understand what is called survival
幫助我們了解到什麼叫做試者生存
So these are the times to study viruses
所以這些都是研究病毒的時候
very interesting for some reasons
非常有趣的一些原因
In the end, of course
那最後當然就是說
if we can understand it
如果我們能夠了解它
If you know yourself and your enemy
那知己知彼的話
Of course we can apply it in reverse
當然我們就可以反過來應用它
That can be said in different fields
那可以在不同的領域上面的話
to find a way to use it
去想要辦法利用它
and then do what we want it to do
然後來做我們希望它做的事情
That's because there are many types of viruses
那因為病毒的種類很多
I just said Wang Fuwen
那剛剛王富文我說
Are there 100,000 or 200,000 types of viruses?
病毒有沒有十萬種 二十萬種
then i just
那我剛剛就
I don't know how many tens of thousands of viruses there are
我不知道說真正的病毒有多少萬種
But basically we can imagine what we just mentioned, that is,
不過基本上我們可以想像剛剛提到就是說
Whether it has 50,000 or 100,000 species
不管它有五萬種還是十萬種
just mentioned that is to say
剛剛提到就是說
it has to change
它必須要改變
if it starts with five
如果它開始是五
It creeps more and it creeps less
它一徐變多它一徐變少
But the point is that it has to keep changing
不過重點就是它必須不斷的改變
Then break through to get a new balance
然後突破得到新的平衡
Then the virus we are mainly talking about today
那我們今天主要談的這個病毒
It's actually Douban
其實就是豆瓣
This may not be a virus that you often hear
這個可能對大家而言不是常常聽到的病毒
It may be less talked about in newspapers and magazines
在報章雜誌上面也許講得比較少
Then if we look at the classification of viruses
那如果我們看病毒的分類的話
Generally we will divide by his genetic makeup
一般我們會以他的基因組成來分
This is a basic
這是一個最基本的
That is, if he is
也就是說如果他是
ribonucleic acid as his genetic makeup
核糖核酸當作他的基因組成
the way words are copied
複製的方式的話
Let's call him RNA virus
我們就叫他RNA的病毒
If he uses deoxyribonucleic acid
如果他是以去氧核糖核酸
as his genetic makeup
當作他的基因組成的話
Let's call him a DNA virus
我們就叫他DNA病毒
Then everyone in Taiwan often hears that
那大家在台灣常常會聽到說
Viruses, kids have diarrhea
長病毒啊小孩子拉肚子
or flaviviruses like dengue virus
或者是黃質病毒像登革熱病毒
retroviruses like HIV
反轉路病毒像我們講的HIV
Ebola virus, he is a very virulent
伊波拉病毒他是一個毒性很強的
or flu virus
或者是流感病毒
Whether it's love flu
不管是情流感
or human influenza virus
或者是人的流行性感冒病毒
These are all RNA viruses
這些都是屬於RNA病毒裡面
Then their mutations are actually faster in general
那他們的突變其實一般來說是更快
Then the virus we are going to talk about today
那我們今天要講的病毒
Actually a DNA virus
其實屬於DNA病毒
What about DNA viruses?
那這個呢去氧核糖核酸的病毒
it's easier for you to hear
你比較容易聽到就是
e.g. herpes virus
比如說像包疹病毒
That mouth sometimes breaks
那個嘴巴有的時候會破
that is
那個是
He also uses deoxyribose to diagnose viruses
包診病毒他也是用去氧核糖
nucleic acid as his genome
核酸當做他的基因組
What about the pox virus we are talking about today?
那我們今天講的痘病毒呢
right in this corner
就在這個角落
He also uses DNA
他也是用DNA
Then he is in this corner because now
那他排在這個角落是因為現在
He probably knew that ten or fifteen years ago
他大概一知道十年十五年前的時候
he is
他是
We can always say he is the biggest virus
我們一直可以說他是最大的病毒
Now there is an amoeba-infected
那現在有一種感染阿米巴的
mimi virus
叫做咪咪病毒
that becomes the biggest virus
那個變成最大的病毒
so he is the second most virus
所以他是第二大的病毒
ok, then this reflects
ok 那這反映出來就是說
Its size is large because of its complexity
他的體積大因為他的複雜度
And after he is in the middle of the evolution process
還有他在演化的過程中間之後
It will talk to these small viruses of another Spectrum
就會跟另外一個Spectrum的這一些小的病毒
Strategy that may be used on evolution
可能在演化上面利用的Strategy
that
那個
not the same
就不太一樣
Then we will discuss a few today
那我們今天會討論到幾個
It is more related to our human society
跟我們的人類社會比較有關係的
One is the smallpox virus
一個就是天花病毒
The general virus is divided according to his records
那一般的病毒跟著他的記錄來分
what about our pox virus
我們的痘病毒呢
If he is infected with vertebrate
如果他是感染了脊椎類的
right here
就排在這邊
If it's an insect infestation, it goes here.
如果是感染昆蟲類的就排在這邊
What are we talking about today?
今天我們談的幾個呢
it's all here
都是在這邊的
the first is to look at the other
第一個就是看看另一個
Smallpox virus inside history
在歷史裡面的天花病毒
Although the smallpox virus is currently
天花病毒雖然目前是說
out of human society
離開人類的社會
we are in society
我們在社會裡面
In fact, there is no such thing as smallpox virus anymore.
其實已經沒有所謂的天花病毒
spread in the human world
在人類的世界傳播
But in history
不過在歷史裡面的時候
It is probably the most vicious virus
它大概是最兇狠的一個病毒
From a historical point of view
那從歷史上面來看的話
It's actually a very old disease
它其實是一個非常古老的疾病
its history presumably goes back
它的歷史大概可以回到
1200 BC
西元前1200多年
that there is no direct evidence
那沒有直接的證據
looking at indirect evidence
看的就是間接的證據
The most important piece of evidence
那這最主要的一個證據
That is to say, in ancient Egypt
就是說在古埃及的時候呢
This Pharaoh Ramus V
這個法老王Ramus V
On the face of his mummies
他的那個牧乃伊的臉孔上面
in fact here
事實上在這裡
some like
有一些像是
acne scar marks
痘的疤痕的痕跡
and places like these
還有像這些地方
That's actually a scientist who tried to
那事實上是有科學家試著去
want to be able to get from the top of these skins
想要能夠從這些皮膚的上面
Try to see if you can separate
試著看能不能分離出來
genes of some viruses
一些病毒的基因
but so far
不過到目前為止
Haven't heard any positive news yet
還沒有聽到有正面的消息
what they separated
他們分離出來的東西
It's still normal
都還是一般的這個
uninfected skin
沒有感染的皮膚上面
So the current technology is of course hoping to find
所以現在的科技當然是希望能尋求
more direct evidence
更直接的證據
But with a symptom like his
不過以他這樣子的一個表現出來的病徵
can almost be deduced to say
在可以幾乎可以推到是說
around 1200 AD
大概西元一千兩百年的時候
in human society
人類社會裡面的時候
There are already traces of the smallpox virus
就已經有天花病毒存在的痕跡
what about the other one
那另外一個呢
There is also no direct evidence
也是沒有直接的證據
However, according to historians
不過根據歷史學家的記載
At this time of 4400 BC
在這個西元前四千四百多年的時候呢
Athens vs Sparta
雅典跟斯巴達打仗
that often
那常常呢
War is a so-called
戰爭就是一個這個所謂的
A hotbed of activities like Pluck and Virus
Pluck跟病毒這些活動的溫床
Although we just mentioned
雖然我們剛剛提到說
Viruses often like to mutate
病毒常常喜歡突變
and then be able to adapt to his life
然後能夠適應他的生活
But in the middle of the process
可是在這過程中間的時候
Human beings are absolutely pushing and blocking
人類絕對是推波阻攔
because once the war
因為一旦打仗之後
whole living conditions
整個的生活條件
man's permanence
人的永久度
Then what about living conditions
然後呢生活條件
Hygienic conditions have all declined.
衛生條件全部都居然下降
So that's basically a hotbed of spread.
那這基本上就是傳播的溫床
So in this historian's record, when
所以在這個歷史學家的記載裡面的時候
they will often refer to
他們會常常提到是說
human body, especially limbs
人的身體尤其是四肢
there will be some erythema
會有一些紅斑
Then what
然後呢
they have a fever
他們會發燒
the whole thing is
出整子就是
Most obvious in smallpox is its
最明顯的在天花就是它的
The farther away from the mid-birth zone
越遠離生期中區的時候
it's whole will be more
它的整子會越多
Those like these are basically some descriptions above
那像這一些基本上都是一些形容上面
let everyone deduce that
讓大家推論是說
In fact to the vid
事實上到了西元
four hundred years ago
四百多年前的時候
Smallpox has already begun to spread in Europe
天花就已經在歐洲裡面開始衡行
In fact, China also has the so-called
那中國其實也有所謂的
this smallpox record
這個天花的記錄
That's probably around this B.C.
那大概是在這個西元前
more than three hundred years ago
三百多年的時候
that time
那個時候
because he thought he came in from the outside
因為他認為他是從外面進來的
So it's called Lu Chuang
所以叫做魯窗
Then what
然後呢
he had one of the earliest
他是有一個最早的
A process on a written record
一個文字記錄上面的一個過程
When Ge Hong entered the court
這個葛鴻在進朝的時候呢
he often writes
他常常寫
He wrote many books about medicine
他寫了很多醫學有關的書
you speak now
你用現在的話講
He's probably a pretty good epidemiologist.
他大概是個很好的傳染病學家
or an epidemiologist
或者是流行病學家
Because he didn't just record
因為他其實不只是記錄了
This possible smallpox situation
這個可能天花的狀況
He actually recorded
他其實還記錄了
Like rabies or an immediate hoof stab
像狂犬病或者是立刻刺蹄一下
some other infectious diseases
一些其他的感染疾病
Some conditions that develop in patients
在病人身上的發展的一些狀況
According to the interpretation of ordinary people, this book
那這個書根據一般人的解釋
kind of like a
就有點像是一個
I wear this on my hand after I leave
這個走後就戴在手上的
Then a first aid manual looks a bit like this
然後一個急救手冊有點像這個樣子
There are some words in it
那裡面就形容了一些詞
what about these words
那這些詞語呢
Basically, it is similar to smallpox in modern times
基本上就會跟天花在現代的時候的一些
Development looks relevant
發展看上去很有關係
He said he had a sore and his face was in a hurry
他說發瘡 頭面急生
because it is systemic
因為它是全身性的
Xu Yu Zhou Zha
虛於周紮
it's all over
它全身都是
Strong as a fire window
壯如火窗
Because it actually has some redness
因為它事實上會有一些紅種的現象
Then in the white chapter there will be
接在白章裡面會有
melt this liquid
融這個液體
Take it with you
隨絕隨身
As long as it breaks, it will fall apart again
只要破裂了就會再散開
If not cured, those who refuse will die
如果不治 拒者多死
So the death rate is actually very high
所以這個死亡率其實是很高
That
那
Don't talk about today we say we are in China
不要講說今天我們說在中國了
In fact, when in Europe
那事實上在歐洲的時候
or
或者
in America
在美洲
This smallpox was actually
這個天花事實上在當時
It is a very serious social disease
都是一個非常嚴重的社會的疾病
We mentioned that in more than 100 AD
我們提到是說在西元一百多年的時候
In fact, a very famous man named Antony Pluck
其實一個很有名叫Antony Pluck
That's the fact that we're back again
這就是事實上我們又回來講了
this is the roman empire at war
這是羅馬帝國打仗
What about the time of war?
那打仗的時候呢
Of course it's a waste of time
那當然又是百廢待局
So what about the people in the city?
那所以城裡面的人民呢
Because it's hard to count that number
因為很難去統計那個數字
But history books record about 30% of the population
可是史書記載大概三成的人口
In fact all rose because of smallpox
事實上都因為天花而上升了
then in this situation
那在這個情況的時候
In fact, the Roman Empire has no way to survive
這個羅馬帝國事實上就沒有辦法survive
his power
他的強權
You can see that it is said in history
你可以看到是說在歷史裡面的時候呢
In fact, only disease does not distinguish between rich and poor
其實只有疾病是不分貧富貴賤
I colleagues
一世同仁
So there is no distinction between Chinese and foreign in history
所以在歷史裡面不分中外
In fact, there are quite a few of these palace nobles and even kings
其實有相當多的這些皇宮貴族甚至國王
He actually had some symptoms of smallpox when he died
他死的時候其實就是具有天花的一些病徵
Then of course in this case
那當然在這種情況的時候呢
There is no such thing as the burial etiquette of the royal family.
就已經沒有所謂的王族這個陪葬的禮儀
Then all the common people and their relatives
那所有的老百姓還有自己的親屬
and inheritance
還有繼承
The sons of the throne are practically shunned
王位的兒子事實上都避之為恐不及
That was a lot of times
那這也是當時很多的時候
Their historians have documented such a process
他們的史學家有記載這樣子的過程
So you can see that is
所以你可以看到就是說
at that moment
在那個時候
In fact, the toxicity of this disease has nothing to do with its dissemination
其實這個疾病的毒性跟他的散播性
In fact, it is already in everyday life
其實已經是每天生活裡面
must encounter
必須要碰到的東西
So even if
所以就在即使是
It can also be seen in the literature
文獻裡面也可以看得到
a record like this
這樣子的一個記載
in this record
在這個記載裡面
The traces of smallpox on a girl's face
天花在女孩子的臉上留下的痕跡
written down and quoted
被人寫下來引用
puppy on black flower
小狗在黑色的花
So this smallpox
所以這個天花
with a horror shot
帶著一個恐怖的一個注射
Level Terrors at the Fair
Level Terrors at the Fair
to this beautiful girl
對這個美麗的女孩子
scary look at it like this
可怕的這樣看一看
or give her some threatening scares
或者是給她具有威脅性的一些驚嚇
Rifle every use for grace
Rifle every use for grace
In these young and elegant bodies
在這些年輕又優雅的身上
attack
攻擊
left the remand of a face
left the remand of a face
so left some marks on the face
所以在臉上留下了一些痕跡
So in fact no matter in the medical record
所以事實上不管是在醫學的記錄上面
Or in fact, the textual research on the literature
或者其實是文獻的考據上面
can see the ceiling
都可以看得到天花
In fact, many records have been left in human society.
其實在人類社會裡面留下了很多的記錄
That day the flowers arrived in America is actually a
那天花到了美洲其實是一個
It's actually quite a feeling that this
其實是一個相當讓人感覺這個
this very sad story
這個非常悲傷的故事
because when we are infected
因為我們在感染的時候
There is a concept that
有一個觀念就是說
If today a whole group
如果今天一個整個的群體
It doesn't have any herd immunity of its own
它本身沒有任何的群聚的免疫力的話
It has never seen a virus like this
就它從來沒有見過這樣子的一個病毒
or when a bacterium
或者是一個細菌的時候
Once you have a full-scale invasion
你一旦全面性的入侵的時候
In fact, there is no resistance at all
其實就完全沒有抵抗力
when in america
那在美洲的時候
In fact, this is the case
其實情況就是如此
Because when European immigrants entered from Spain
因為歐洲的移民從西班牙進去的時候
When entering from Central and South America
從中南美洲進去的時候
met the indians of south america
碰到了南美洲的印第安人
Of course it's because the culture is different
那當然因為文化的不一樣
Many times they will initially
很多的時候他們一開始會
would be in awe of these Spanish immigrants
會很敬畏這些西班牙的移民
then later
那到了後來的時候
There will be conflicts and wars
中間會有衝突打仗
Among the immigrants brought
那帶來的這些移民裡面
someone has smallpox
就有人已經得了天花
So it was passed on to the local aborigines
所以就傳到當地的原住民的身上
So in fact at that time
所以在那時候事實上
two major empires
兩個最主要的帝國
Azac and the so-called Inkars
Azac跟所謂的Inkars
The two South American cultures
那這兩個南美洲的文化
In fact within a few decades
事實上在幾十年之內
In fact, because of the invasion of smallpox
事實上就已經因為天花的入侵
disappears soon
很快的就消失了
Then smallpox's footprint goes from South America and up
然後天花的足跡就從南美洲再往上走
that went to north america again
那又進入了北美洲
When it entered North America
那進入了北美的時候
British immigrants, of course, took smallpox
英國的移民當然就把天花
Brought to the New World
又帶到了新大陸去
When taking to the New World
帶到新大陸去的時候
Indigenous Indians actually have
印第安人員住民其實有
once allied with the armies of france
曾經跟法國的軍隊聯盟
hope to drive the british away
希望把英國人給趕走
The result is in the middle of the process
結果就在這個過程中間的時候
England has a general
英國就有一個將軍
Called Jeffrey Amist
叫做Jeffrey Amist
he moved one
他就動了一個
a bad thought
一個壞的念頭
he thought
他就認為說
I can't win the battle today
今天我仗打不贏了
I can't convince these aborigines to cooperate with me
我也說服不了這一些原住民跟我合作
Then their extravagance
然後他們的虛索無度
what should I do
我怎麼辦
So he conspired with several people
所以他就幾個人密謀
These are all documented
那這些都是有一些文獻的記載
in fact they
事實上他們就
very famous is
很有名的就是
They sprinkled the smallpox virus on this
他們把天花的病毒灑在這個
straight up
坦直上面
then sent to the aborigines
然後送給原住民
That aborigines got this
那原住民就得了這個
So in fact the entire Tribe is here
那所以事實上整個的Tribe在這裡就
was greatly affected
就受到很大的影響
So this is probably our human history
所以這個大概是我們的人類史上
You can see the first very malicious exploit of smallpox
你可以看到第一個非常惡意的利用天花
as a so-called biochemical record
當作一個所謂的生化戰績
that threat
那這個威脅
Of course it is very small in terms of the current perspective
當然是很小以現在的眼光而言
But we came back to say that
不過我們又回來提到就是說
if you today
如果你今天
In a group, there is no resistance at all
在一個群聚裡面是完全沒有抵抗力的時候
History like this is very likely to repeat itself
這樣子的歷史是非常可能重演
Then come another history of human beings
那再來這麼一個對人類的歷史
have such serious influence
有這樣子嚴重影響性
how is it contagious
它究竟是怎麼傳染的
is it possible
是不是可以
To avoid such an infection or to prevent
避免這樣子的傳染或者是預防
When it was contagious, we just mentioned
那傳染的時候其實我們剛剛提到
because of his
因為他的
his
他的
E-roll is his sneeze
E-roll就是他的打出去的噴嚏
In fact, it can be dispersed in the air
其實在空氣裡面是可以散布的
It is also recorded in the history that
那歷史裡面也有記載說
In fact, in the hospital environment
其實在醫院的環境裡面
Just like SARS at that time
就像那時候的SARS一樣
In fact, they do have a hospital
其實他們的確是有醫院裡面
Some evidence of cluster infection
群聚感染的一些證據
The most common is actually the so-called
那最常見的其實就是所謂的
easy contact
輕易的接觸
family
家人
Then or touch him
然後或者是接觸碰到他的
These things that appear when you are sick
這個生病的時候出現出來的這些
these homes
這些家
or infected clothing
或者是感染的衣物
When people like this are actually exposed to infection
像這一類其實接觸傳染的時候
often there will be
常常就會有
doesn't seem to have much to say today
似乎並沒有很多說今天
smallpox depends on food
天花是靠食物
by eating or drinking
靠吃或者是靠喝水
It seems that there is no such direct evidence
好像好像比較沒有這樣直接的證據
Generally speaking, what we just mentioned
那一般來講就是我們剛剛提到的
way of infection
的感染的方式
Then there's another thing, it's actually the virus.
那還有一點其實是這個病毒
A very important feature is the
非常重要的一個特性是
he can't help
他沒有辦法
leaning on insects
靠著昆蟲
Or run with other animals
或者是靠著其他的動物來帶著跑
So this point is that we humans can exterminate smallpox
所以這一點是我們人類能夠滅絕天花
a very very very important reason
一個非常非常非常重要的一個原因
That is to say, today it is trapped in this
也就是說今天它被困在我們的人類的這個
In this ancestor worship environment
這個祭祖的環境裡面
If today it can run elsewhere
如果今天它可以跑到別的
other animals
別的其他的動物身上待著
Then wait until the future to jump back into human society
然後等到將來再跳回人類社會的時候
Then it will be very difficult for you to exterminate such a virus
那你就非常難去滅絕這樣子的一個病毒
so it is so far no
所以它是目前為止是沒有
Didn't know it could use insect bites
並不知道說它可以用昆蟲的叮咬
or springtails or other animals to deliver
或者是跳蟲或者是其他的動物來傳遞
This is a limitation of the smallpox virus
這個是一個天花病毒的時候的限制
Then its influence on that disease
那它在那個疾病上面的影響性
In fact, smallpox is because of the current molecular biology
其實天花因為現在這個分子生物學
very developed
非常的發達嘛
So many times in the early days in the hospital
所以很多時候以前早期在醫院裡面
Some virus strains in the hospital will be isolated
會分離出來一些在醫院的一些病毒株
people now
現在人就
take it all out
全部拿出來
Then he reordered the
然後他重新用定序的方式
find a way to get some of this
想辦法把這一些
These viruses in the previous hospital
以前醫院的這一些的病毒
all sequenced
全部都定序出來
Then you can see their comparison
然後可以看他們的比較
Then basically we can put
那基本上我們可以把
Smallpox is divided into two categories
天花分成兩大類
more serious category
比較嚴重的一類
its english name is
它的英文名字叫做
Smallpox
Verola Major
If those ten people are probably infected
那十個人裡面大概感染的話
three to four people will die
會死三到四個人
So the death rate is about 30% to 40%.
所以死亡率大概是三成四成
The other category is called Verola Minor
那另外一類呢叫做Verola Minor
Its death rate is lower
那它的死亡率就比較低
about 1%
大概是1%
So in fact, in many diseased plants, when
所以事實上在很多的病株裡面的時候
while on the internet
現在在網路上面的時候
Most of them are actually the sequence of Verola Major
大部分很多其實都是Verola Major的sequence
Then many scientists will be in these sequences
那很多的科學家就會在這些的序列裡面
to find some possible clues
去尋找一些可能的線索
Sorry, there will be a few more later
那不好意思後面會有一幾張
Although everyone just had dinner
雖然大家剛剛吃過晚飯
may be a little uncomfortable
可能會有點不舒服
That's basically what we walked through very quickly
那基本上我們很快的走過就是這個
make you feel
讓你感覺一下就是說
This is actually a human disease
這個其實是一個人類的疾病
Then when you saw the course of these illnesses
那你看了這些的病症的過程的時候
Actually you will understand this
其實你會理解到這個
this virus is fast
這個病毒之快
It goes on fast in our body
它在我們的身體裡面發病之快
probably terrible
大概是很可怕的
That means today
那也就是說今天呢
its what we call
它的 我們講的所謂的
this incubation period
這個潛伏期
Its disease is divided into several levels
它的病就分成幾個層次
What about the incubation period?
潛伏期呢
Actually, you can't see anything sick about it.
其實是 你看不見它有任何生病的狀況
The second one is about to get sick.
那第二個就是快要發病了
May have some symptoms
可能有一些些的症狀
But the skin is still
可是皮膚上面還是
not so obvious
並不是那麼的明顯
And most importantly of course
然後最重要的當然就是
It has a variety of this blob itself
它有各式各樣的這個斑點的本身
in the middle of this process
這個過程中間
Because of its shape it is divided into different stages
因為它的形狀就分成不同的階段
What about these stages?
那這些的階段呢
go the whole way the whole way
整個走完整個的全程
about two to three weeks
大概是兩到三個禮拜
Then there is one more thing in the middle of this process
那還有一件事情在這個過程中間
What scientists have discovered is that
科學家發覺到的就是說
The incubation period we just talked about
我們剛剛講的潛伏期
about seven to ten days
大概是七到十天
during this time
在這段時間的時候
The patient is not infectious
這個病人是沒有感染力的
That is to say, during this time
也就是說在這段時間的時候
actually it goes everywhere
其實它到處走
The chances of it infecting others are actually not very good.
它感染別人的機率其實是不太好
That's the same as the influenza virus
那這一點就跟那個流行性感冒病毒
Or other viruses are very different
或者其他的病毒是很不一樣
Many times it is like the tuberculosis we talked about
很多的時候像我們講的肺結核
it sometimes has no needles
它有的時候是沒有病針
Then this person may actually be infected.
那這個人可能其實已經有感染力
He is when he goes around
他 可是他到處去走的時候
you do not know
你不知道
Then he will infect more people
那他就會傳染更多的人
But smallpox is the other way around
可是天花是反過來
When he didn't have this sick needle
當他在沒有這個病針的時候
In fact, his infectious power is high
其實他的感染力是高的
Then I knew he started to have a fever
那一知道他開始有發燒
Then these homes on the surface
然後表面上的這些家
Start with some flat pillows
開始從原來的一些平平的枕
then to the raised pillow
然後到凸起來的枕
Then go inside and start having
然後到裡面開始有
fluid inflamed fluid
有液體 發炎的液體
Hua Nong
然後到化濃
After the last dry
到最後乾了以後
Run away from home
脫家 流疤
in the middle of the process
這個過程的中間呢
his contagiousness
他具有的感染力
the experiments they did
他們曾經做過的實驗
probably look at that
大概看一下就是說
When these organizations
這一些組織的裡面的時候
You can see the yellow line telling you
你可以看到黃色的線告訴你
really contagious
真正具有感染力
Usually it's his surface that's already showing up
通常就是他的表面已經出現了
Then you can imagine that
那這個你可以想像就是說
If a person is walking down the street
如果一個人在街上走的時候
when he was covered with scars
他身上都是疤的時候
everyone will stay away from him
大家一定會遠離他
So this spread of the virus
所以這個對病毒的傳播
Actually it's not a good thing
其實並不是一個好的事情
Well, of course you can also imagine
那這個你當然也可以想像說
Later, when the United Nations, everyone in the world
到後來的時候聯合國大家全球
when trying to eradicate smallpox
試著要去滅絕天花的時候
To observe patients with smallpox
對觀察天花的病人
This is also a very important condition
這也是一個很重要的條件
That is to say
也就是說
That is to say, these medical staff
也就是說這些醫護人員
In fact, they can quickly see that
事實上他們可以很快的就看得出來說
who might start to be contagious
誰可能開始要具有感染力
then you can go
然後就可以去
Go to the main character's contact with other people
去主角他跟其他人的接觸
This is the time to help him limit his walks
這個是幫助他限制他散步的時候
a very important condition
一個很重要的條件
The other one is to wait for him, of course, to get to know the house.
那另外一個就是等他當然到了解家的時候
In fact, these homes are actually contagious.
其實這一些家事實上也是具有感染力的
Then we just mentioned that
那我們剛剛提到是說
He is divided into several types
他分成幾個Type
The death rate we are talking about is relatively high
我們講的死亡率比較高的
Called Veirola Major
叫做Veirola Major
Then he has one we call
那他有一個我們叫做
The most common is called Odinary Type
最常見叫做Odinary Type
a lot of it is on the flying nose
很多是在飛鼻身上
Actually in Europe
其實在歐洲的時候
Also when this smallpox entered Europe
也這個天花進到歐洲的時候在
When Northern Europe and Western Europe
這個北歐跟西歐的時候
many times
很多的時候
You'll see his mortality inside when
你會看到他的死亡率裡面的時候
A very high percentage are children
很高很高的比例都是小孩子
Then of course we can guess
那我們當然可以猜測
That is to say, the development of children's immunity
就是說小孩子的免疫力的發展
actually weaker than adults
事實上是比成人來得弱
what about the other
那另外呢
In fact, relatively rare
其實比較少見的
I think you often read it in textbooks
我想大家看常常有時候會在教科書上看
The relatively rare one is actually called Flat type
比較少見的其實這種叫 Flat type
It doesn't actually have what we just mentioned
它其實並沒有我們剛剛提到的
ginger or strong
薑或者是濃
Well it's actually a rash all over
那它事實上整個像皮疹一樣
very thick
非常的厚
And then this patient
然後呢這個病人
In fact it's a very serious kind of
事實上這是一個非常嚴重的一種
form of smallpox
天花的形式
Because the patient is actually in a coma
因為這病人其實就陷入昏迷
then in fact
然後呢事實上
It's not like this
已經比較沒有這樣子
able to respond
能夠有反應
the third one is scarier
那第三個是更可怕
It's called Hemorrhage
它叫做 Hemorrhage
Hemorrhage is
Hemorrhage就是
just bleeding
就是出血
bleeding disorder
出血症
that is, it bleeds under the skin
也就是它會有皮下出血
or systemic hemorrhage
或者是全身性出血的一些
some phenomena
一些現象
Generally speaking
那一般來講的話
The meaning of this may be that it
這個的含義可能就是說它身上
In addition to the spread of the virus
除了病毒的散佈之外
Possibly some immune-inflammation
可能還有一些免疫發炎的
some other role
一些其他的作用
in progress
在進行
That's because it's a person's background
那因為這是一個人的底細
And because in fact this
然後因為其實這個
These smallpox are actually a stunt now
這些天花現在其實都已經絕技了
So we actually
所以我們其實
Looking back on such a dangerous disease
回過頭來對這麼危險的一個疾病
In fact, we don't know much about
其實我們的了解其實是不多的
because of its danger
也就是因為它的危險
So it caused a distance for us to study it
所以造成了我們去研究它的一個距離
So in fact, even today
所以其實到今天雖然說
It currently does not exist in human society
它在人類的社會裡面目前是沒有
But we have a lot of serious pathology like this
可是我們對很多這樣子嚴重的病理
In fact, its nature is still unclear.
其實它的本質其實還是不清楚的
that just mentioned
那剛剛提到就是說
This is some of them from CGC
這個是CGC的他們一些
Some clinical diagnoses
一些臨床上面的一些診斷的時候
They will find that just mentioned
他們會發覺剛剛提到
Once the current situation of bleeding occurs,
一旦有出血的這種現狀發生的時候
Almost 100% will die
幾乎百分之百就是會死亡
If it was the spleen diagnosis just mentioned
那如果是剛剛講的脾診的時候
It also has a particularly high mortality rate
它的死亡率也是特別高
The rest is about 30% to 50%
那其他的大概就是三成到五成
It's the Virula Major we're talking about
就是我們講的Virula Major
Of course, if today you have had acne before
那當然如果今天你因為以前曾經中過痘
Then your symptoms will be slightly relieved
那你的症狀就會稍微得到舒緩
That
那
Of course you don't need to talk
當然不用講
It is said that smallpox will actually have some sequelae
說天花其實會有一些後遺症
i remember when i was little
我記得當我小的時候
In fact, Taiwan also has smallpox
其實台灣也是有天花
because my mother is a friend
因為我母親一個朋友
She actually had smallpox when she was little
她其實小的時候就得過天花
Those who stay can often see
那留下來的常常都會看得到
There are scars on the face
就是臉上的會有疤痕
So these are actually right
那所以這一些其實對
common people's social
一般人的社交上面
In fact, it has a very large impact
其實是有非常大的影響
But for those who do epidemiology
可是對做流行病學的人而言
This is actually what they said in the trace
這個其實就是他們去trace說
the disease in this village
這個疾病在這個村落
or this disease in this city
或這個疾病在這個城市
or how long the disease has developed in this place
或這個疾病在這個地方發展了多久
Then if you want to contain them
那如果要去contain他們
They are actually some data
他們其實這些是一些數據
with some research directions
跟一些研究的時候的方向
In other words
那另外來講的話
There is another side effect
還有另外一個副作用
That is because his infections are often systemic
就是說因為他的感染常常是全身性的
So there will be some people
所以也會有一些人在
Although the disease is cured
病雖然好了之後
His cornea
他的這個眼角膜
In fact, after being affected, there is blindness
其實受到了影響之後是有失明
or limbs
或者是四肢
Because of some of the inflammation we just mentioned
因為我們剛剛提到的一些發炎
or some festering condition
或者是一些潰爛的狀況
Will have some physical effects
會產生一些肢體上面的影響
some disabilities
一些殘障
Then there are often times in the clinic
那常常有在那個臨床上面的時候呢
It is often said that smallpox often
常常有說這個天花常常會
we fight virus
我們講鬥病毒
Sometimes with my colleagues or
有時候跟我的同事或
when chatting
聊起來的時候
they will say
他們會說
Is Zhang Wenshuidou also fighting viruses?
張文水豆是不是也是鬥病毒
Then I want to say solemnly
那我要鄭重在就是講
Water beans are not fighting virus
水豆不是鬥病毒
Mizumame
水豆
I don't know why he is called Shui Dou in Chinese
我也不知道為什麼中文翻他叫水豆
Probably more water
大概水比較多
That English is called chicken pops
那英文叫做 chicken pops
You just turn it over and it's chickpeas
你直接翻就是雞豆
Then he actually belongs to the
那他其實是屬於我們剛剛提到
He is also a DNA virus
他也是一個 DNA 的病毒
But he is a herpes virus
可是他是屬於抛疹病毒
So that's a noticeable difference
那所以這是一個明顯的差別
Of course beans are different
當然豆子不一樣
These are also distributed differently
這些還有散布的狀況不一樣
These have clinical differences
這些都有臨床上面的差異
that's right
那可是對
If we divide this virus into categories
我們如果分這個病毒類來講的話
The smallpox virus we just mentioned
我們剛剛提到的天花這個病毒
He is usually on the patient
他通常一般來講在病人身上
It is unlikely that there will be some medical history of so-called previous infection
是不太會有所謂以前感染的一些病史
Because usually the first time
因為通常就是第一次就
it's serious and you can see it
就很嚴重你就看得見
But when it comes to chickenpox, these shingle pillow viruses
可是對水痘這些帶狀泡枕病毒的時候
Usually we get chicken pox when we are very young
通常我們得到水痘都是非常小的時候
And what about this virus?
然後這個病毒呢
after posting
發了之後呢
it goes to the ganglia in your body
它會進入你身體裡面的神經節
it hibernates there
它就冬眠在那個地方
Then our body immunity actually suppresses it
那我們身體免疫事實上會壓制的它
so it stays inside the original cell
所以它留在原來的細胞裡面
no harm to us
對我們沒有什麼的傷害
but peaceful coexistence
可是和平的共存
Then wait until you stay up late to study
那等到你熬夜念書
get ready for the forest
準備森林啊
then what
那然後呢
Meishuibao
叫眉睡寶
Then what
然後呢
When your immune system goes down
你的那個免疫系統下來的時候
it comes up
它就上來了
Therefore, when many children come to the exam
所以很多的小孩子到考試的時候
Just a lot of holes in the mouth
就嘴巴一大堆破洞
what about this
那這個呢
wait until you are immune
等到你免疫好了
and temporarily clear it
又可以暫時把它清掉
it's back to that lurking place
它又回到那個潛伏的地方
So these different viruses
所以這些不同的病毒
It may represent the same
它也許表徵好像一樣
but it is actually
可是它其實是
are two completely different ones
是完全兩個不同的那個
The words here are actually true for some if
那這裡的話其實對一些如果是
If there is someone who is more interested
醫有比較有興趣的人的話
Their mental retardation can be compared
他們的智障可以比較分得出來
That is to say, smallpox is actually long
就是說天花它其實長
The whole one that came out was swollen like this
出來的整隻都是這樣腫起來的
And it's not actually like inside the beans
然後它其實並不是像水豆裡面
It's just that its water content is more
就只是它的水的成分比較多
words here
在這裡的話
In fact, it has more concentration and experience in the back
它其實到後面都比較有化濃跟體驗存在
The second one is the distribution we just talked about
那第二個就是我們剛剛講它的分布
This is a smallpox in the medical field
這是一個天花在醫療上面當初
very important demarcation point
非常重要的一個分界點
That is to say, many diseases will cause blisters
就是說很多的病都會長泡
assortment of bubbles
各式各樣的泡
Why is it called this Smallpox
為什麼它叫這個Smallpox
In fact, the earliest is because in ancient times
其實最早是因為古時候的時候
There is another one called Largepox
另外有一個叫做Largepox
That's syphilis
那那個就是梅毒
There will be a picture of the beans produced by the syphilis later
待會會有一張那個梅毒產生的豆子
so their bean shape
所以他們的豆子形狀
In fact, we look pretty much the same
其實我們看都差不多
People in the medical field see it differently
醫療界的人看是有差別的
in terms of smallpox
那以天花而言的話
its obvious one is the bean it's diseased on
它很明顯的一個是它發病的豆子
usually away from your middle crispy body
通常會離得你的中酥這個身體
the farther it goes the more
越遠的地方它會越多
you can think about this
那這個你可以去想
We don't know it's the blood circulation
我們不知道是跟血液循環
Or with the tissue of these cells
還是跟這些細胞的組織
what's the special relationship
有什麼特殊的關係
But it's obviously going to be in the head
不過它就是很明顯會在頭
will be in hand
會在手
and then at...
然後會在...